Jose Paul

B1 208, Majestic Residency, Taverekere Main Road .Bangalore 560029

Mobile: 9448248135

Email: josekavunkal@gmail.com

Passport No: H8210605

Experience Summary

Over 22 years of experience in IT industry. Had worked in Architecture and development of Core Java /J2EE and also NodeJs IOT applications. . My experience mainly spans into product development and API development in Java, Phython and Node.js and is well conversant with analysis and design using OO methodologies, UML and Design patterns. Worked with clients from countries like US ,UK ,Middle East, Japan etc.

Coding Dojo Experience :Completed two (IOT and Fintech) cohort successfully .Currently joined as TA in Software Development cohort .

Career Objective.

To work as teacher and enjoy the happiness of sharing.

Education

B.E (Production Engineering -1997)	Kerala University, Kerala India
BSc (Mathematics) -1993	Calicut University, Kerala

Technical Skills

Operating Systems / Network	Windows, Solaris and, Linux			
IDE	Eclipse, NetBeans, Creator and Forte			
Application Server/ Internet	Jboss, Apache, JDBC, JavaScript, Threading, Spring, BlueMix, IOT,			
Technologies/Technologies/Pro	Cloud ,Django,Node-Red, Micro services ,UIOT, MQTT,			
tocols	Coap,DevOps,REST			
Languages	Java, NodeJS,Python,React ,C#			
Cloud	AWS VPC setup,EC2 management,Application deployment			
	,Lambda,S3			
Web Servers	Java Web Server2.0, Apache, Tomcat			
Build Tool	ANT			
Frameworks	Eclipse Plugin, Spring Boot, Spring Cloud ,DJango			
Source code versioning	RTC, Clear Case, GIT			
systems				
Other Tools	Good knowledge on Kafka, Kubernetes, Docker,AWS,Serverless			
Database	Oracle, MySQL, DB2, noSQL, dashDB,postgres			

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

1.Current Freelancing ,currently working with microfacturingusa.org and Coding Dojo

Position Held : Teaching Assistant Full Stack application AWS/cloud

Developer/Architect/Trainer.

Duration : Nov 2018 till date.

2 Organization : HPE India Private Ltd.

Position Held : Architect.

Role : Lead IOT demo team.
Duration : Nov 2016 Nov 2018

Architect Page 1 of 10 Jose Paul

3. Organization : India Software Labs, IBM India Private Ltd. Position Held : Advisory Software Engineer. (Architect)

Duration : Jan 2011 till Nov 2016

4 Organization : Blue Star Infotech (CMM Level 5 Company),.

Position Held : Senior Consultant
Duration : May 2004 to Jan 2011

Deputation

Organization : SUN Microsystems Bangalore.
Position Held : Consultant from Blue Star Info Tech.
Role : Onsite Coordinator/Team Lead

Duration : Oct 2005 to Jan 2011

5 Organization : Exor Italy.

The India development center of Exor, a Italian based software development company specializing in Industrial Automation Software and having international development centers. (http://exor-rd.com,

http://exorindia.com/)

Position Held : Team Leader

Duration : Aug 1999 to May 2004

6. Organization : Tangent Software, Vashi, NaviMumbai

Position Held : Java Programmer
Duration : Nov 1997 to July 1999

Project Profiles Project 1

Project	IoT Creator Platform(Node-red) development			
Client Name	microfacturingusa.org			
Environment	Nodejs, Node-red,AWS			
Team Size	6			
Role	Platform development/deployment in AWS,backup/restore in S3,AWS EC2 capacity planning and management. Own the whole development ,deployment ,customer support and infrastructure setup. Training in IOT			
Duration	March 2020- Till date			

Project Description

IoT Creator Platform is Node-red based product deployed in AWS. This is IOT training platform where students can create their own instance of Node-red in AWS.

Project 2

Project	UIOT Platform Development Arcitect ,Demo development lead
Client Name	HPE India Private Ltd
Environment	Java, Python , Nodejs, Node-red
Team Size	8
Role	IOT Demo Lead ,Tool Development ,POC ,IOT Platform deployment
Duration	Nov 2016- Nov 2018

Project Description

UIOT platform development .Developed multiple IOT demos like connected car, Smart City ,Vehicle Architect Page 2 of 10 Jose Paul

Tracking etc. This role also include deployment of IOT Platform components and multiple HPE IOT related products. Good knowledge on hardware (sensor integration, RPI, Arduino etc) and required software for developing a demo .

Project 3

Project	Watson IOT Platform		
Client Name	India Software Labs ,IBM India Private Ltd		
Environment	Java 1.8		
Team Size	8		
Role	IOT Demo ,Tool Development ,POC		
Duration	May 2013- 2016		

Project Description

Watson IOT platform and tools development. Demo development with drones, RPI powered connected car, sensors, motors Etc. Have traveled across India to demonstrate IOT capabilities of Watson platform.

Project 4

Project	IBM JCC Driver (JDBC type 4 Driver).			
Client Name	India Software Labs ,IBM India Private Ltd			
Environment	Java 1.8			
Team Size	14			
Role	CRM lead .Design and development ,IBM Django, SQLAlchemy open source component owner. IOT POC and Demo ownership.			
Duration	Jan 2012- Jan 2013			

Project Description

JCC driver is used by java application to connect to DB2 databases .This is a Type 4 JDBC driver .This is a highly complex product managed by Indian team .

Responsibilities

- · Design and Development
- Team Lead for customer issues
- Code review

Challenges.

- Since this is a driver, quality is very important also risk is very high.
- Multi-Threaded application ,increases the complexity ,
- Analysis and fix of defects which spans multiple layers.

Project	IBM Optim Database Administrator		
Client Name	India Software Labs ,IBM India Private Ltd		
Environment	Java 1.6,Eclipse		

Team Size	22
Role	Project lead /Architect
Duration	Jan 2011- January 2012

ODA is a tool which is developed as a plugin in Eclipse and is designed to use for administration of databases. The tool can perform all database administration tasks like, taking backup, Quiesce ,etc

Responsibilities

- Lead the project.
- Scrum Master
- Design and development.
- Code review

Challenges.

- Team spread across the world, coordination is challenging.
- · Assuring code quality.
- Clear Case issues.

Project 6

Project	LIFEGUARD		
Client Name	SUN MICROSYSTEMS		
Environment	Java 1.6,Swing,AWT,JSF,JPA,MySQL,EJB		
Team Size	6		
Role	Project lead /Architect		
Duration	Oct 2005- Jan 2011		

Project Description

The project include providing guide lines to developers, also guide the customers to finalize architecture .The program also include providing module level design guide lines.

The customers include internal clients as well as external SUN customers.

Responsibilities

- Provide insight into overall Architecture of the project.
- Guide the client to troubleshoot application level issues.
- Design core modules.
- Fix developer issues.

Challenges.

- Collaborative approach: Work with different teams and gather information, in stipulated time.
- Managing client pressure.
- Simulating issues at our end.

Project	SDD Table Editor
Client Name	Communication And Technology Systems (CATS), Japan

Environment	Java 1.4, eclipse 2.1.2, GEF and Windows 2000, Draw2D.
Team Size	12
Role	Project Leader/Architect
Duration	May 2004-Sep 2005
Methodology	XP / Agile

This is a set of Eclipse based (Eclipse Plugin) Editors which are used for configuring Embedded System. All editors looks like Excel and is having some of the features Of Excel like column hiding, cell editing, etc. The model used for the editors is EMF. Editors display data in tables of different structures and user can edit the data using dialog box, this will update the EMF model and notification will be send to all interested object to update their UI. The system is designed in MVC Architecture.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements elicitation and analysis.
- Provide the architecture
- Guide the team to design modules.
- Manage requirement and design changes.
- · Mentored junior programmers.
- Solving complex issues
- Weekly status reporting and ensure timely delivery.
- Motivating the team
- Offshore Co-ordination, Estimation, Tasks allocation and tracking.

Challenges

- Design of core modules which automatically create the UI as per the structure of Model.
- Requirement management: Streamlined a process for requirement exchange.
- Weekly delivery
- When requirement keeps on changing the code throw away happens frequently and team get De-motivated.
- Japanese data
- Moderating pressure. Since the project is executed in XP model the pressure was very high.
- Bugs in the framework API.

$\overline{}$					_
ப	roi	$^{\circ}$	\sim	r	•
_	ıvı	ᆫ	u	L	•

Project	State Machine Chart Diagram
Client Name	Communication And Technology Systems (CATS), Japan
Environment	Java 1.4, Eclipse 2.1.2, GEF and Windows 2000, Draw2D.
Team Size	12
Role	Project Lead
Duration	May 2004-Oct 2004
Methodology	XP / Agile

Project Description

UML Modeler (Eclipse Plugin) is an IDE based on the Eclipse platform, specifically engineered towards developing State Chart Diagram. User can drag and drop components from the Tool Bar and develop a State UML diagram. GEF is used for creating and editing the Diagram. Ultimate aim is to generate C Code from the XMI generated.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements elicitation and analysis.
- Provide the architecture

- Guide the team to design modules.
- Weekly status reporting and Ensure timely delivery.
- Mentoring and motivating the team.
- Estimation
- Solving complex issues
- Offshore Co-ordination, Daily client Interaction through mails and phone calls to solve issues and bug fixing.
- Scheduling, tasks allocation and tracking.

Challenges

- Moderating stress level of developers under XP model.
- This was pilot project and we are supposed to prove ourselves by completing the project in short duration.
- XMI generation routine from model.

Project 8

Project	Device Studio
Client Name	EXOR Italy
Environment	Eclipse, JDK 1.4, XML, XPath
Team Size	10
Role	Project Leader
Duration	Sep 2002 to May 2004

Project Description

Device Studio (Eclipse Plugin) is an IDE based on the Eclipse platform, specifically engineered towards developing C/C++ programs for remote Embedded Devices running eCos. This IDE is capable of debugging remote programs running in MIPS hardware. The IDE can connect to the remote hardware using TCP\IP or Serial Connection, download the program to be debugged into the hardware and run it. Real-time monitoring of the hardware registers and memory locations is possible. The IDE can also be used for configuring the board parameters.

Responsibilities:

- Requirement gathering/analysis and Use Case preparation.
- Feasibility study.
- Design / Development and Coding of most all the modules.
- Solving complex issues
- Weekly status reporting and ensure timely delivery.
- Done Code walk through.
- Mentoring and Motivating Junior programmers.
- Estimation and Planning. This includes preparation of WBS.
- Managed two teams and at two location, one at Bangalore and other at Cochin.
- Scheduling using MPP.
- Resourcing
- Procurement and maintenance of the health of the hardware with updated software.

Project	WCP
Client Name	EXOR Italy
Environment	JDK 1.4, SVG, XML, SOAP, JScript.
Team Size	11
Role	Team Leader
Duration	Feb 2002 to Sep 2002

Web Control Panel (WCP) is designed to monitor and control industrial parameters obtained from remote sensors. It consists of a web-browser client and a main Server program. The Server is directly connected to the data logging devices on the remote machines. The client is designed to display/manipulate elements using SVG plug-in in an HTML page. JScript is used for client-side manipulations. SOAP protocol is used for communication between the client and server. A script library is used on the client side for processing SOAP messages. The display components include Buttons, Meters, Selector switch etc. to control and monitor status of a remote device.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements Analysis.
- Involved in design of all the modules.
- Coding
- Mentoring junior programmers.
- Ensure timely and quality delivery.
- Estimation and Planning
- Co-ordination among team members
- Client management.

Project 10

1 10,000 10	
Project	EGOIDE
Client Name	EXOR Italy
Environment	JDK 1.4, Swing and XML.
Team Size	7
Role	Team Leader
Duration	June 2001 to Jan 2002

Project Description

Egolde is a Java Based Swing Application which generates (device independent) SVG Images. The application is used to create SVG Images of software controls like Switches, Knobs, Meter, etc. The entire SVG data and interaction scripting is done automatically. Drag-and-drop UI design and pop-up interactivity design methods are used. Jazz is used as the rendering engine.

Responsibilities:

- · Requirements analysis.
- Prepared requirement specification document.
- Involved in design and development of all the modules.
- Team Co-ordination
- Estimation
- · Mentored junior programmers.
- Ensure timely delivery.

Project 11

Project	E-Ghost
Client Name	Client: Net solutions Kochi
Environment	JDK 1.3, HTML, JSP, EJB, WebLogic, CORBA, Oracle and XML.
Team Size	6
Role	Team Leader
Duration	Feb 2001 to June 2001

Project Description

E-commerce shopping cart application using J2EE 1.0. This is a distributed application which mainly consists of J2EE servers & HTML/WML clients. Buyers and Sellers can register themselves and participate in on-line transactions. WebLogic 5.0 is used for application server. A unique transaction verification process is built in using WAP devices.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Design , Development and Co-ordination

Project 12

Project	Pigeon Express
Client Name	Client: Net solutions Kochi
Environment	JDK 1.3, HTML, Servlets, JSP, XML
Team Size	8
Role	Team Leader
Duration	Aug 2000 to Jan 2001

Project Description

This is an intranet mail server application. Mail Client is designed in HTML and server side using Servlets. Mail headers are stored in XML (DOM) and mails in text format. An important feature of the project is mail read-out capability. The server application has a controller card that listens for incoming TAPI requests. It then accepts the DTMF codes. A user can dial and login to the system from his home, retrieve list of mails and get the server to read out the new mails.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Involved in design of all the modules.
- Co-ordination
- Estimation
- Codina
- Mentored junior programmers

Project 13

Project	MetaSim
Client Name	EXOR Italy
Environment	JDK 1.2, Swing, RMI, JavaBeans etc.
Team Size	6
Role	Team Leader
Duration	Feb 2000 to July 2000

Project Description

A system, which can be used to control electronic devices with the help of s/w controls. It consist of a Visual Editor to design pages with different types of controls. Controls are JavaBeans which can be selected from the toolbox and can be dragged and placed in the workspace. The editor is similar to Bean Development Kit. This is a real time system, which is used for Controlling and monitoring embedded systems. This is Client/Server system. Both are Java applications. Server is connected to the embedded system with the help of a Java - OPC Bridge.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Design
- Co-ordination

Project	Uniop Simulator
Client Name	EXOR Italy

Environment	JDK 1.2 ,Applet
Team Size	9
Role	Team Leader
Duration	Aug 1999 to Feb 2000

This system is developed for EXOR Italy. This is a web based client/server system. It is used for controlling programmable Electronic devices through Internet. Web browser sends request to the server, which in turn sends information about the current state of the electronic machinery. The Client is an Applet and the server is an application. Applet uses a well-defined protocol to talk with the server. The Server will be running in the device (Embedded System) to be controlled. It contains pages with Software Controls, which is sent as per the client request. Client can switch to any of the pages and can control the device with the s/w controls displayed in the Applet.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis and design
- Coordination
- Multi-Threading implementation.

Challenges

- To solve performance issues of the application.
- Splitting the system to maintainable modules.

Project 14

Project	PDF Editor
Client Name	Tangent Software. Mumbai
Environment	JDK 1.2, Java 2D and Swing.
Team Size	5
Role	Programmer
Duration	Feb 1999 to July 1999

Project Description

Multi-window Swing application used for electronic publishing of text and graphics in PDF format. This system can be used to design and layout pages with text and graphics. The designed pages can then be saved in a particular format which is then parsed by another software, which generates the PDF file

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Design and Development
- Coordination

Project 15

Project	TAD Designer
Client Name	Tangent Software. Mumbai
Environment	JDK 1.2, Java 2D and Swing.
Team Size	3
Role	Programmer
Duration	May 1998 to Jan 1999

Project Description

A computer aided designing software for architects. This software can be used for designing buildings. This is a Java Standalone Application. The GUI of this system is designed in Swing. Basic graphics components that go to make a building can be dragged and dropped to the workspace. After designing the structure, the file is serialized and saved.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Design and Development
- Coordination

Project 16

Project	TAD Reader
Client Name	Tangent Software. Mumbai
Environment	JDK 1.2, Java 2D and Swing.
Team Size	3
Role	Programmer
Duration	Nov 1997 to May 1998

Project Description

TAD Reader sectioning software was developed at Tangent Software, Navi Mumbai. This software is exclusively for architects, by which they can take sections of the buildings wherever needed, without drawing each section after the completion of the design. This is a standalone application, which reads the project file designed with TAD Designer and converts it into objects. User can interactively define the plane where he/she needs the section. The system will find out the object that comes in that plane and will take a section. The section is rendered as Vector Graphics that can be zoomed to any desired scale.

Responsibilities:

- Requirements analysis.
- Design
- Co-ordination
- Optimization.
- Coding